[MUSIC]
[음악]
Great. We talked about an application of finding
좋습니다 지금까지 이미지 특징을 활용해
cool shoes or dresses just based on image features.
멋진 신발, 드레스 찾아봤습니다
The technique that we're gonna use today is called deep learning.
오늘 사용할 기법은 딥러닝이라고 합니다
And in particular it's based on something called neural networks.
그중 신경망이란 걸 씁니다
But before we get there, let's talk about data representation.
그전에 데이터 표현법을 설명드릴게요
We discussed things like TFIDF and
TF-IDF와 단어주머니(Bag-of-words) 모델을 알아봤는데
bag of word models, but how do you really represent data when it comes to images?
이미지라면 어떻게 데이터를 표현해야 할까요?
These are called features, and is a key part of machine learning.
특징이라 불리는 이게 기계학습의 핵심입니다
So typically, when you talk about machine learning, we're given some input.
일반적으로 기계학습이라고 하면 입력이 주어집니다
Let's say we're doing classification, we talked about sentimental analysis.
분류 작업을 할 텐데 감성분석은 했었죠
You're giving a sentence, it goes through a classifier model and
문장이 주어지면 분류기 모델에 통과시켜
we decided that sentence has positive or negative sentiment.
긍정적, 부정적 감성인지 결정했습니다
In image classification, the goal is to go from an image,
이미지 분류에서는 입력인 이미지 픽셀을
this is my input, the pixels of the images, to a classification.
통해 분류를 하는 것입니다
In this case, this is my dog and I want to classify it as
이건 제 개인데 래브라도 리트리버인지
a Labrador retriever as opposed to other kinds of dogs.
다른 종류인지 분류하고자 합니다
So as we discussed, features are the representation of our data
특징은 데이터 표현법이며
that's use to feed into the classifier.
분류기에 입력됩니다
There are many representations, so for example text,
많은 표현법이 있는데 텍스트에는
we talked about bag of words and TFIDF.
단어주머니와 TF-IDF가 있었죠
With images there's a lot of other representations.
이미지에는 다양한 표현법이 존재합니다
And we'll discuss a few more of those in this module.
이 모듈에서 그중 몇 개를 설명합니다
But today we're really gonna focus on neural networks,
오늘은 신경망에 집중하기로 하죠
which provide the non-linear representation for the data.
데이터의 비선형적 표현법을 제공합니다
Now,let's go back to classification.
분류로 다시 돌아가죠
Let's do a little review.
복습을 좀 해봅시다
We discuss linear classifiers which create this line or
선형 분류기는 이런 선을 긋거나
linear decision boundary between say the positive class and and the negative class.
긍정 클래스, 부정 클래스 사이의 선형 결정 경계를 설정합니다
And the boundary is stated by the score, w0 +
경계는 점수 w0 + w1 * x1 + w2 * x2로
w1 x the first feature, x1 x2 x the second feature and so on.
이어지는 수식으로 표현됩니다
On one side, on the positive side, the score is greater than zero and
점수가 0보다 높은 긍정 클래스와
on the negative side the score is less than zero.
0보다 낮은 부정 클래스로 나눠집니다
So, if I have this nice score function,
점수 함수가 있으면
I can separate the positives from the negatives.
긍정과 부정을 나눌 수 있습니다
In neural networks we're going to represent such classifiers using graphs.
신경망에서는 이런 분류기를 그래프로 표현합니다
And so, here we have a node for each feature x1, x2, all the way
x1, x2에서 d번째 특징 xd까지 각각 노드가 있고
to the dth feature, xd, and a node for the output y, which we are trying to predict.
예측하고자 하는 결과값 y 노드가 있습니다
So, the first feature x1 is multiplied by the weight w1, so
첫 특징인 x1에
I'm putting that weight on the edge.
간선의 가중치 w1을 곱합니다
X2 is multiplied the second weight, w2 I'm gonna put it on that edge,
x2에는 두 번째 간선 가중치 w2 하는 식으로 해서
all the way to xd, which is multiplied the weight wd, to put in the last edge.
xd에 마지막 간선의 가중치 wd 를 곱합니다
And the last weight, w0 doesn't get multiplied by any feature, but it gets
마지막 가중치 w0은 특징과 곱하지 않고
multiplied by the number one, so we put a little one at the top multiplying w0.
1을 곱하므로 맨 위에는 1을 적습니다
And so, if you imagine multiplying the weights, w0 through wd
가중치 w0에서 wd까지를
with the features x1 through xd and the coefficient one, you get the score.
특징 x1부터 xd, 계수 1까지 곱하면 점수가 나옵니다
And when the score is greater than zero, we declared the output to be one and
점수가 0보다 크면 결과값이 1이 되고
when it scores less than zero, we declare the output to be zero.
0보다 작으면 결과값이 0이 됩니다
This is an example of a small, one layer, neural network.
이건 간단한 단층 신경망입니다
So, we describe the small linear classifiers as a neural network,
선형 분류기를 단층 신경망으로
as a one layer neural network.
나타냈습니다
What can this one layer neural network represent?
What can this one layer neural network represent? 단층 신경망으로 뭘 표현할 수 있죠?
Let's take the function x1 or x2.
함수 x1 OR x2를
Can we represent that using a small neural network like this?
신경망으로 나타낼 수 있나요?
Well, let's define the function a little bit more formally.
함수를 좀 더 엄밀하게 정의할게요
So, what we have is variables x1,
변수 x1, x2와
x2, and the output y.
결과값 y가 있습니다
And there's some possibilities.
몇 가지 가능성이 있죠
X1 can be zero, x2 can be zero, and since it's x1 or x2,
x1이 0이고 x2가 2이면 x1 OR x2니까
the output y would be zero in this case.
결과값 y는 이 경우 0가 됩니다
When x1 is one, and x2 is zero, the output is one.
x1가 1이고 x2가 0이면 결과값은 1입니다
When x is zero, when x2 is one, the output is one,
x1가 0이고 x2가 1이면 1이고요
and similarly, when they're both one, the output is 1.
마찬가지로 둘 다 1이면 1입니다
So, we want to define the score function such that the value is greater
마지막 세 행의 값이 0보다 크지만 첫 행에서는 0보다 작은
than zero for the last three rows, but it is less than zero for the first row.
점수 함수를 정의하고자 합니다
How do we do that?
어떻게 해야 할까요?
So for example, there are many ways of doing it actually, but
사실 아주 다양한 방법이 있지만
if I put a weight of one.
가중치 1을 각 간선
When each one of the edges x1 and x2, and we think about the score, the score
x1, x2에 매기고 점수를 보면
of the first row is zero and the score of the other rows are greater than zero.
첫 번째 행의 점수는 0이고 다른 행들의 점수는 0보다 큽니다
So, we wanna add a little bit of separation, so
분리해야 하니
we might put a negative value on the first edge.
음수를 첫 번째 간선에 할당합니다
Let's say -0.5 and so let's see what happens to the score.
-0.5라고 하고 점수가 어떻게 변화하는지 보죠
When x1 is zero and x2 is zero, then the score becomes -0.5 and
x1가 0이고 x2가 0일 때 점수는 -0.5이니
yey I have something less than zero and my score is correct, my output is correct.
결과는 0보다 작습니다 점수도 맞고 결과값도 맞네요
When x1 is one and x2 is zero, I get the score of 0.5.
x1가 1이고 x2가 0이면 점수는 0.5입니다
Similarly, when x1 is zero and x2 is one.
x1가 0이고 x2가 1이여도 같고요
And finally when they're both one, I get a score of 1.5.
마지막으로 둘 다 1이면 점수는 1.5입니다
So, with this simple weights on the edges, I represent the function x1 or x2.
간선 가중치만 가지고 OR 함수를 표현했습니다
Now, can we represent the function x1 and x2?
AND 함수도 표현할 수 있나요?
Well, similarly we can put weights one and one on the edges x1 and
비슷하게 가중치 1을 각각 간선 x1와 x2에 주는데
x2 but in this case, we only want to turn it on when both x1 and x2 have value one.
이 경우 x1와 x2가 둘 다 1일 때만 1이 돼야 하므로
So, instead of putting -0.5 on that top edge, we put -1.5.
가장 윗 간선에 -0.5 대신 -1.5을 줍니다
And, if you fill out the table just like we did with the first example,
똑같은 방식으로 표를 채워보면
you'll notice that we now represented the function X1 and
신경망을 통해 AND 함수가
X2 using a simple neural network.
표현됨을 확인할 수 있습니다
So, a one layer neural network is basically the same as the standard
단층 신경망은 지금까지 배운
linear classifiers we've been learning about in this course so far.
보통의 선형 분류기와 같습니다
So what can linear classifiers not represent,
선형 분류기가 표현하지 못하는 게 뭐지요?
we said it can represent x1 or x2.
OR는 가능하다고 했죠
It can represent x1 and x2 but what's a function,
AND도 가능했죠
a very simple function it cannot represent?
표현 못하는 간단한 함수가 있나요?
Well, here's an example.
예제 하나 드릴게요
There is no line that separates the plusses and minus in this example.
선 하나만으로 플러스, 마이너스를 분리하는 건 불가능합니다
This function's called the XOR.
이 함수는 XOR라고 합니다
I like to call it the counter example to everything.
저는 모든 것에 대한 반례라고 부르는데요
So, whenever you're trying to find the counter example,
반례를 찾고 싶을 때
the first thing to try is XOR.
제일 먼저 XOR를 대입해 봅니다
Now, for this case, the linear features we described are not enough and
이 경우 선형적 특징으론 충분하지 않아서
we need some kind of non-linear features, and this is when
비선형적 특징을 찾아야 합니다
you're networks come to play for reals and we'll see an example of that.
신경망이 활약을 하게 되는데 그 예를 지금부터 보죠
So let's review what XOR is.
XOR이 뭔지부터 복습할까요
So, XOR has value one when either X1 is true and
XOR는 x1이 참이고 x2가 거짓이거나
x2 is false so not x2 or not x1, so
NOT x2이거나 NOT x1일 때
x1 is false or zero and x2 has value 1.
x1이 거짓, 또는 0이며 x2가 1일 때 1이 됩니다
So, how can we represent this with a neural network?
신경망으로 어떻게 표현할까요?
Well, let's call this first term z1 and the second term z2.
첫 번째 항을 z1, 두 번째 항을 z2라고 합시다
What we're gonna do is build a neural network to represent
이제 신경망에서 직접 입력 x1, x2를
not directly the inputs x1 and x2 to predict y, but
통해 y를 예측하는 게 아니라
don't predicts intermediate values z1 and z2, and then those are going to predict y.
중간값인 z1, z2부터 구한 다음 이를 통해 y를 예측합니다
So let's take z1.
z1부터 보죠
How do we represent a neural network, only a neural network that can predict z1.
z1만을 예측하는 신경망을 어떻게 표현할까요
We discussed that a little bit, but here goes.
좀 전에 설명드렸지만 한번 더 해보죠
It's a little bit different than the end case from before.
AND와는 조금 다릅니다
Since, we have to negate, we say not x2, we put a minus 1 on that edge and
반대값을 취해야 하니 x2에 -1을 주고
we put a plus 1 on x1 and a minus 0.5 in there.
x1에는 1, 여기는 0.5를 줍니다
We now have our representation for z1.
z1를 이렇게 표현할 수 있습니다
Similarly for z2, we put a minus sign on the edge x1,
z2에는 간선 x1에 마이너스 기호를 붙이고
this edge here, x1 to z2, we put a plus one on the edge x2 to z2 and
x1에서 z2로 가는 이 간선입니다 간선 x2-z2에 +1를 준 다음
then -0.5 on the constant edge, and now it represents z2.
상수 간선에는 -0.5을 주면 z2이 완성됩니다
And the last step, if Z1 is it to exist, all we have to do is or them.
마지막으로 z1과 z2가 있으면 그 둘을 OR하기만 하면 됩니다
And we already know how to or to bullien variables.
불 변수에 OR 하는 건 이미 알죠
It's just one, 1- 0.5.
1, 1에 0.5를 빼줍니다
And this is an amazing time for us.
의미 있는 순간입니다
We've now built out first deep neural network,
첫 번째 신경망을 만들어 봤습니다
not super deep, has two layers but is a little exciting.
2층밖에 없어 아주 깊지는 않지만 그래도 놀랍습니다
We just built our first neural network.
신경망을 처음으로 만들어 봤고요
It was a two layer neural network, but in general neural networks about,
2층 신경망이었는데 일반적으로 신경망에는
there's layers and layers of transformations of your data.
데이터 변환을 위한 수많은 층들이 존재합니다
And we use these transformations to create these non linear features, and
이런 변환을 통해 비선형 특징을 찾아내는데
we'll see some examples of that in computer vision.
컴퓨터 비전에서 몇몇 예를 볼 겁니다
Now, neural networks have been around for
신경망은 거의 50년 가깝게 우리 곁에 있었으니
about 50 years, about as long as machine learning's been around.
기계학습이 생겨난 시기와 비슷합니다
However, they fell is disfavor around the 90's because
하지만 90년대에 인기가 시들해졌는데
folks are having a hard time getting good accuracy in neural networks.
연구자들이 신경망으로 그다지 정확도를 높이지 못했기 때문이죠
But everything changed about ten years ago,
10년 전쯤 모든 게 바뀌었는데
because of two things that came about.
두 가지 요인이 등장했기 때문입니다
First, it was a lot more data and because neural networks have so many, many,
먼저 데이터가 훨씬 증가해서
many more layers.
신경망에 층을 엄청나게 늘릴 수 있었습니다
So, many layers you need a lot of data to be able to train all those layers.
층이 늘어나면 데이터가 많아야 훈련이 가능하죠
They have a lot of parameters.
파라미터가 많으니까요
We'll see a really exciting neural network of 60 million parameters.
6천만 파라미터의 신경망을 보게 될 겁니다
So, we need a lot of data to train them.
그러니 훈련 데이터가 무척 많이 필요하죠
So, we recently have come about lots and lots and
최근 들어 이런 엄청난 데이터를
lots of data from a variety of sources, especially the web.
웹 등 여러 채널을 통해 구할 수 있게 됐습니다
Now, the second really great change that made deep neural networks possible
두 번째로 컴퓨팅 자원이 발전하여
is advances in computing resources.
딥 신경망이 가능해졌습니다
Because we have to deal with bigger neural networks and more data,
신경망이 커지고 데이터가 늘어남에 따라
we need fast computers and GPUs which were originally designed for
빠른 컴퓨터와 GPU가 필요해졌습니다
accelerating graphics for computer games.
GPU는 원래 컴퓨터 게임 그래픽 가속을 위해 설계됐죠
Turned out to be exactly the right tool to build and
알고 보니 많은 데이터를 처리하는
use neural networks with lots of data.
신경망을 만드는데 안성맞춤이었습니다
So because of GPUs and
GPU와
because of these deep neural networks, everything's changed.
딥 신경망 덕분에 모든 게 바뀌었습니다
And now we've had a lot of impact in the real world.
실생활에 큰 영향을 끼쳤죠
[MUSIC]
[음악]